<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Accruing technical credit</title><link href="https://rotocki.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://rotocki.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://rotocki.github.io/</id><updated>2019-07-14T16:20:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>First steps with Pelican to set up this GitHub Page</title><link href="https://rotocki.github.io/first-steps-with-pelican-to-set-up-this-github-page.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-14T16:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-14T16:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Remik</name></author><id>tag:rotocki.github.io,2019-07-14:/first-steps-with-pelican-to-set-up-this-github-page.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;My first steps to have this GitHub page set up using Pelican&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title first"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#making-first-steps-in-a-virtual-environment" id="id1"&gt;Making first steps in a virtual environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#creating-the-project-and-figuring-out-its-structure" id="id2"&gt;Creating the project and figuring out its structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#simplifying-serving-procedure-with-invoke-and-its-tasks" id="id3"&gt;Simplifying serving procedure with invoke and its tasks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#uploading-the-page-to-github" id="id4"&gt;Uploading the page to GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#changing-github-page-s-source-to-a-publishing-branch" id="id5"&gt;Changing GitHub page's source to a publishing branch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="making-first-steps-in-a-virtual-environment"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id1"&gt;Making first steps in a virtual environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a little bit of reading to see if it is possible to setup
my own GitHub page without having to resort to Ruby/Jekyll since
I'm much more comfortable with doing stuff in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I'm trying to use a bit more restructuredText to eventually write
all of my documentation for Python code in a syntax that is Sphinx-friendly,
I wanted to have that option to write the content in rst files instead of
plain HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the assumptions above, I decided to use Pelican and see how far
will I get with it. First step was to install it and see how many other
plugins and/or dependencies will I need to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do is to install all the dependencies in a virtual
environment so that if this experiment fails, I can just remove
the folder with the environment in it instead of going through
dependencies in my system and cleaning them one by one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've been installing a typical virtual environment, an idea came to my mind.
I was about to create a project which focuses on doing one thing only while being run
always in the same environment is the ideal definition of an application.
Since there is a great tool to keep all dependencies for an application
in a controlled fashion, I thought about managing it using &lt;cite&gt;pipenv&lt;/cite&gt; instead.
I've used it in the past for a bit but never really committed to it.
Because this idea sounded like a good one, I decided to run with it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pip install pipenv
pipenv install pelican
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="creating-the-project-and-figuring-out-its-structure"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;Creating the project and figuring out its structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After installing Pelican in the virtual environment, I checked how to start
the project rolling. Fortunately, there is a quickstart step similar to the one
you can find in Sphinx.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run pelican-quickstart
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've configured the project in such a way that I customized the title,
author and made sure that it correctly refers to my GitHub page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the quickstart was done, I looked at the structure of the project.
I created a simple &lt;strong&gt;About me&lt;/strong&gt; page under &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;content/pages/about.rst&lt;/tt&gt;
and this blog post under &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;content/blog/first-steps-with-pelican-to-set-up-this-github-page.rst&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.
I followed the typical &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/stable/content.html#file-metadata"&gt;File metadata&lt;/a&gt; structure for the blog post
and a simplified version for &lt;strong&gt;About me&lt;/strong&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that everything should be simple, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run pelican
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've looked at the generated HTML files stored in output folder in project's default path.
To my surprise, opening just the &lt;cite&gt;index.html&lt;/cite&gt; file wasn't as pleasant as I expected,
since all of the other static content like CSS were not collected by the browser.
Opening checking the documentation, I've noticed that I was supposed to serve the pages
on web server instead of just browsing them directly. Sounds logical. The immediate
suggestion was to do it by moving to output directory and running HTTP server
from Python 3's standard library:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;/content $ python -m http.server
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I just opened my browser and checked the page served as &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;localhost:8000&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="simplifying-serving-procedure-with-invoke-and-its-tasks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Simplifying serving procedure with invoke and its tasks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The page worked correctly but I was not satisfied with this approach as it seemed error-prone.
First I needed to make sure that I'm inside a correct folder and then remember to invoke
&lt;cite&gt;server&lt;/cite&gt; module from &lt;cite&gt;http&lt;/cite&gt; library. So I looked for another approach in the files autogenerated
by pelican with quickstart procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I've worked a bit with &lt;cite&gt;invoke&lt;/cite&gt; package and used fabfiles in the past,
I immediately noticed &lt;cite&gt;tasks.py&lt;/cite&gt; file in main directory of the project.
After skimming through the code, I found &lt;cite&gt;build&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;serve&lt;/cite&gt; tasks which would enable me
to generate and serve output files without needing to think about platform/OS on which the tasks
would have to be run on. This sounded great as I'm using Windows whenever I can and resort to
Linux virtual machine only if I have to suffer the performance hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use this approach, I had to install &lt;cite&gt;invoke&lt;/cite&gt; package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv install invoke
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, the procedure to run invoke tasks was wonderfully simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run invoke build
pipenv run invoke serve
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we make it shorter? Sure! As this use case is probably one of the most frequently used
there is already a &lt;cite&gt;reserve&lt;/cite&gt; task prepared and because typing &lt;cite&gt;invoke&lt;/cite&gt; is such a hassle,
we can already use a shorthand &lt;cite&gt;inv&lt;/cite&gt; to save the time needed to type &lt;cite&gt;oke&lt;/cite&gt; at the end of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run inv reserve
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Works as expected. How great is that, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="uploading-the-page-to-github"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Uploading the page to GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that hassle, it would be great to finally share this page with others.
The creation process of a GitHub page is described in great detail in one of the official
guides titled &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://guides.github.com/features/pages/"&gt;Getting Started with GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; so I'll save some time and skip it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's clone the remote repository in the main folder of our project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git init
git remote add origin git@github.com:rotocki/rotocki.github.io.git
git fetch --all
git checkout origin/master -b master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing that, we should be able to commit our changes on top of whatever
we have autogenerated by GitHub during creation of the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git add .
git commit -m &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Initial page.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
git push
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is now version controlled and stored on GitHub...
but the pages are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; visible! What is going on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="changing-github-page-s-source-to-a-publishing-branch"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Changing GitHub page's source to a publishing branch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we think for a moment about a possible root cause of this problem,
we can quickly notice that we don't have an &lt;cite&gt;index.html&lt;/cite&gt; file
in the main folder of our project. Because of that, &lt;cite&gt;README.md&lt;/cite&gt; file
gets served as the &lt;cite&gt;index.html&lt;/cite&gt; page instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back to &lt;cite&gt;tasks.py&lt;/cite&gt; file to see if there is another task that
I can use out of the box and I found one called &lt;cite&gt;gh_pages&lt;/cite&gt; which
is documented as &lt;em&gt;Publish to GitHub Pages&lt;/em&gt;. Jackpot? Looks like it
but I need to understand what is this &lt;cite&gt;ghp-import&lt;/cite&gt; command on which
this task relies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to understand is to check the official documentation
stored under &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/davisp/ghp-import"&gt;ghp-import GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;. After going through the readme
and making sure &lt;em&gt;Big Fat Warning&lt;/em&gt; is understood, I wanted to make sure
that &lt;cite&gt;gh-pages&lt;/cite&gt; branch will be the one used by GitHub as the default one
for serving content. This use case is so frequently used
it has its own section in an article on GitHub Help:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/configuring-a-publishing-source-for-github-pages#enabling-github-pages-to-publish-your-site-from-master-or-gh-pages"&gt;Enabling GitHub Pages to publish your site from master or gh-pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this applies only to project pages and &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; personal
GitHub pages. So we will need to store content in a non-master branch
while our &lt;cite&gt;master&lt;/cite&gt; branch will only contain the output in a way
that can be easily presented to the viewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, let's change the branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git checkout -b content
git push --set-upstream origin content
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the default configuration will make sure that the output
generated from the content stored in a private branch &lt;cite&gt;content&lt;/cite&gt;
will be version under &lt;cite&gt;master&lt;/cite&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I should be able to get away with invoking &lt;cite&gt;gh_pages&lt;/cite&gt; task
but first I have to install &lt;cite&gt;ghp-import&lt;/cite&gt; as one of the dependencies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv install ghp-import
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I can publish my work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run inv gh_pages
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope. Error message: &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;No idea what 'gh_pages' is!&lt;/tt&gt;
There is a task in &lt;cite&gt;tasks.py&lt;/cite&gt; but it cannot be found. Maybe &lt;cite&gt;invoke&lt;/cite&gt;'s can help us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run invoke
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to be &lt;cite&gt;-l&lt;/cite&gt; parameter which should understand us what tasks
are available and how we should call them. After running&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run invoke -l
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
Available tasks:

    build        Build local version of site
    clean        Remove generated files
    gh-pages     Publish to GitHub Pages
    preview      Build production version of site
    publish      Publish to production via rsync
    rebuild      `build` with the delete switch
    regenerate   Automatically regenerate site upon file modification
    reserve      `build`, then `serve`
    serve        Serve site at http://localhost:8000/
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you notice the difference? Underscore magically became a hyphen!
Let's finish the task for today by invoking the &lt;cite&gt;gh-pages&lt;/cite&gt; task!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pipenv run inv gh-pages
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I'm running a Windows 10 machine, the current syntax does not
get accepted and I have to rearrange the quotation marks to get it working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;CONFIG&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Before: &amp;quot;&amp;#39;Publish site on {}&amp;#39;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# After:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;commit_message&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;#39;Publish site on {}&amp;#39;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;today&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;isoformat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After introducing this change, I was able to push the output to &lt;cite&gt;master&lt;/cite&gt; branch
and now you can read this article. Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="pelican"></category></entry></feed>